JENNIFER VÉLEZ SEGURA

Master in Bioinformatics - Biologist

@ jennifervs.bio@gmail.com % https://github.com/jevelezse

+57 314-312-7510 Av Carrera 30 No 39A -60
 in linkedin.com/in/jennifer-velez-segura-34502958/

P Bogotá D.C, Colombia



PROFILE

Biologist with knowledge in classical cytogenetics (karyotypes in bone marrow, amniotic fluid and blood samples) and Master in Bioinformatics. Skills programming in Python, R, and Shell for analysis of biological data and using data mining techniques. Experience in WES and WGS for diagnostic support. Interested in applying machine learning techniques in biological data.

EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatician and Cytogeneticist

Genetix S.A.S

🛗 January 2015 - May 2020

Pagotá D.C., Colombia

- Cytogenetic analysis of samples in peripheral blood, bone marrow, amniotic fluid and chorionic villi.
- Design and implementation of bioinformatic pipelines for the analysis of biological sequences.
- Analysis Whole Genome Sequencing (WGS) and Whole Exome Sequencing (WES).

Cytogeneticist

Biogenética Diagnostica SAS

May 2013 - Nov 2014

- Pagotá D.C., Colombia
- Cytogenetic analysis of samples of blood, bone marrow, amniotic fluid and chorionic villi.
- Sowing and harvesting samples in peripheral blood and bone marrow.

Cytogeneticist

Laboratorio de Genética y Biología Molecular

2013 - 2012

- P Bogotá D.C., Colombia
- Cytogenetic analysis of samples of blood, bone marrow, amniotic fluid and chorionic villi.
- Sowing and harvesting samples in peripheral blood and bone marrow.

MY LIFE PHILOSOPHY

"Problems and looking for solutions are part of life."

MOST PROUD OF



Learn to code

to be able to develop solutions to biological problems.



Learn Machine Learning

and be able to apply it to understand a vareity of datasets.



Being a speaker in Pycon Colombia

and to show other people what can be done with Python and R.



Winner of challenges in data science:

The first challenge Stem Sports y Big Data Colombia 2016 and Winner of the first Hackaton Scotiabank-Colpatria Group Customer segmentation 2018

STRENGTHS

Teamwork.

Problem solving

Continuous learning

Shell

Shiny

Python-Pandas

R-tidyverse/bioconductor

Work in the laboratory

LANGUAGES

English Spanish



EDUCATION

Master in Bioinformatics National University of Colombia

February 2015 - December 2019

Thesis: Association of variants in the regions in genes coding with clinical data in Colombian patients using data mining.

B.S. Biology

Universidad Distrital Francisco José de Caldas

2012

ACHIEVEMENTS



Begin as a student

in Django Girls and then I become a guide, this has been one of the most rewarding experiences of my life



Cabana Travel Fellowships

Scholarship to present the initial model of my master's thesis in Chile 2018



Being evaluator

in ScipyLatam in Bioinformatics area

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

 Venegas, Eliana del Pliar Garzón et al. (2018). "Autopsia molecular en muerte súbita cardiaca neonatal mediante secuenciación de siguiente generación (NGS): presentación de un caso". In: Revista Repertorio de Medicina y Cirugía 27 (1), pp. 39–43.

Conference Proceedings

- Vélez, Jennifer (2019). "Association of variants in coding regions with clinical data in Colombian patients using data mining techniques." In: Conference Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology (ISMB) and European Conference on Computational Biology.
- (2018). "Data mining with clinical and genomic data." In: Pycon Colombia
- Vélez, Jennifer and Elizabeth León (2018). "Association of variants with clinical data in a sample of the Colombian population using the Apriori algorithm." In: ISCB-LA SOIBIO EMBnet.
- Vélez, Jennifer (2017a). "Pipeline for evaluation of coverage in clinical panels exome as quality control alignment." In: IV CONGRESO COLOMBIANO DE BIOINFORMÁTICA Y BIOLOGÍA COMPUTACIONAL Y VIII CONFERENCIA IBEROAMERICANA DE BIOINFORMÁTICA..
- - (2017b). "Python para bioinformática." In: Pycon Colombia.

REFEREES

Andrés M. Pinzón PhD.

- @ ampinzonv@unal.edu.co
- Bogotá D.C, Colombia. U. Nacional de Colombia, Office: 218
- ► +57 (1) 3165000 Ext. 11618 Head of the Master Program in Bioinformatics Group Leader - Bioinformatics and Systems Biology

Luis Fernando Niño V. PhD.

- @ Ifninov@unal.edu.co
- Bogotá D.C, Colombia, U. Nacional de Colombia
- **** +57 (1) 3165000 Ext. 14079/14011 Associate Professor

Cladelis Rubio Gómez. MD.

- @ cladelisrubio@gmail.com
- Bogotá D.C, Colombia
- **८** +57 313 258-9819 MD. Msc Human genetics